<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Two sermons the first preached in Christ-Church, Dublin, Feb. 19, 1681, at the consecration of the Right Reverend Fathers in God, William Lord Bishop of Kildare, William Lord Bishop of Kilmore, and Richard Lord Bishop of Kilalla : the other, preached in the Cathedral Church of St. Patrick, at the primary visitation of the most Reverend Father in God, Francis Lord Arch-bishop of Dublin, Apr. 24, 1682 / by S. Foley ...</title>
            <author>Foley, Samuel, 1655-1695.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 78 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A39854</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F1400</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R2994</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12412856</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12412856</idno>
            <idno type="VID">61584</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A39854)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 61584)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 666:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Two sermons the first preached in Christ-Church, Dublin, Feb. 19, 1681, at the consecration of the Right Reverend Fathers in God, William Lord Bishop of Kildare, William Lord Bishop of Kilmore, and Richard Lord Bishop of Kilalla : the other, preached in the Cathedral Church of St. Patrick, at the primary visitation of the most Reverend Father in God, Francis Lord Arch-bishop of Dublin, Apr. 24, 1682 / by S. Foley ...</title>
                  <author>Foley, Samuel, 1655-1695.</author>
                  <author>Moreton, William, 1641-1715.</author>
                  <author>Sheridan, William, 1636-1711.</author>
                  <author>Tenison, Richard, 1640?-1705.</author>
                  <author>Marsh, Francis, 1627-1693.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 51 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Moses Pitt ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references.</note>
                  <note>"The Epistle dedicatory" to William Moreton, Bishop of Kildare, William Sheridan, Bishop of Kilmore and Ardagh, and Richard Tenison, Bishop of Kilalla.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: second sermon lacking in filmed copy.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Consecration of bishops --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:61584:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:61584:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>TWO SERMONS, The Firſt, Preached in <hi>Chriſt-Church,</hi> Dublin: <hi>Feb.</hi> 19. 1681. AT THE CONSECRATION Of the Right Reverend Fathers in God <hi>WILLIAM</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Kildare, WILLIAM</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Kilmore,</hi> AND <hi>RICHARD</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Kilalla.</hi> The Other, Preached in The Cathedral Church of St. <hi>Patrick:</hi> At the Primary Viſitation of the Moſt Reverend Father in God, FRANCIS Lord Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Dublin, Apr.</hi> 24. 1682.</p>
            <p>By <hi>S. FOLEY,</hi> A.M. Fellow of <hi>Trinity Colledge</hi> near <hi>Dublin:</hi> and Chaplain to His Grace.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Moſes Pitt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> at the Angel in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard. 1683.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:61584:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:61584:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:61584:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="i" facs="tcp:61584:3"/>
            <head>To the Right Reverend Fathers in God, WILLIAM, <hi>Lord Biſhop of</hi> Kildare, WILLIAM, <hi>Lord Biſhop of</hi> Kilmore, <hi>AND</hi> RICHARD, <hi>Lord Biſhop of</hi> Kilalla.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lords,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE Sermon which I had the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to Preach at the Conſecration of Your Lordſhips, I do now Publiſh, in hopes that it may give a little Satisfaction to ſome miſtaken People, who may happen to read it; and I dedicate it to Your Lordſhips, in hopes that Your Lordſhips will demonſtrate, that that is feaſible which I ſay will be expected
<pb n="ii" facs="tcp:61584:4"/>from, and that that Reſpect is deſerved by, which I ſay is due to, thoſe of Your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips Order.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>I am my Lords, Your moſt dutiful and humble Servant,</hi> SAM<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>EL FOLEY.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:61584:4"/>
            <head>A Conſecration SERMON PREACHED In <hi>Chriſt-Church,</hi> Dublin: <hi>Feb.</hi> 19. 1681.</head>
            <head type="sub">The beginning of the <hi>Epiſtle</hi> appointed by the Church for this Service, being</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1.</hi> Timothy, <hi>iii. 1.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>This is a true Saying, if a man deſire the Office of a Biſhop, he deſireth a good work.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>ST. <hi>Paul</hi> having in the preceding Chapters given <hi>Timothy</hi> ſome general Account of the true Faith, and ſuitable Worſhip of God; as a neceſſary means for the continuing and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending of the one, and for the becoming per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of the other, proceeds in this, to treat
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:61584:5"/>of the Government of the Church. And by way of Introduction to what relates to the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Offices, of thoſe perſons who were to be reſpectively concern'd in it, He makes a Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to this purpoſe: That whoſoever deſires to be inveſted with that Power and Authority which of Right belong to the higheſt and moſt eminent of them, he deſires an Employment worthy and honourable, an Office by which he may be enabled to do ſome Service to his great Creator, be a publick Bleſſing to the Age he lives in, a Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer of God's Favours to men, and as it were an Agent to maintain and keep up a Correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence between Earth and Heaven. For this I judge a Paraphraſe not ſtrained on the Apoſtles words, <hi>This is a true Saying,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Being to ſpeak before this great and honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Audience, upon this Occaſion and Subject, I ſhall humbly beg leave to make a modeſt En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry into theſe following particulars.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Whence our preſent Biſhops have their Authority?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Whether Epiſcopacy hath any Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages above other Forms of Church-Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> What may be juſtly and reaſonably expected from Perſons entruſted with that Sacred Authority?</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:61584:5"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> What Honour and Reſpect is due from us to them?</p>
            <p>By what I ſhall ſay in reſolution hereunto, 'twill I hope be plain enough, That <hi>he deſires a good Work, who deſires the Office of a Biſhop.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I begin with the</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt Enquiry,</hi> Whence our preſent Biſhops have their Authority?</p>
            <p>That ever ſince theſe Nations have preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to Adore <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> as their <hi>Lord and Redeemer,</hi> They have, in Obedience to him, Worſhipped God, after a way not known be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, is denied by none. That all who have agreed in this belief and way of Worſhip, have reputed themſelves in <hi>that reſpect, a Community</hi> different from Civil Bodies Politick, is as evident; from their Exerciſing and Submitting to, an Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority diſtinct from all Civil Power. That <hi>Biſhops</hi> have been the Chief meerly Spiritual Governours of this Society, from the very firſt Conſtitution of it here, and that thoſe <hi>Venerable</hi> Perſons whom we now call <hi>Biſhops,</hi> have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd the Spiritual Authority they claim from others of that Order and Title, who received the ſame from their Predeceſſors, and ſo in a continued ſeries, from the firſt entertainment of that Religion in theſe Iſlands (were it neceſſary) might with much eaſe be clearly made out. So
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:61584:6"/>that the Queſtion will be reduc'd to very narrow Terms, <hi>What Authority, and from whom, the firſt planters of Chriſtianity among us, were intruſted with to Communicate to others?</hi> For more full Satisfaction in this matter, it being liable to many miſtakes of evil conſequence, I ſhall lay down what I have to ſay concerning it, in theſe diſtinct and plain Propoſitions.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That <hi>Our Bleſſed Saviour</hi> had <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Authority</hi> to Inſtitute, and Form a <hi>Society</hi> over the whole World, to be governed by ſuch <hi>Laws</hi> and ſuch <hi>Officers</hi> as he ſhould appoint.</p>
            <p>This is evident both from the <hi>Prophecies</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the <note n="(a)" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> ix. 6.</note> 
               <hi>Meſſiah</hi> in the <hi>Old</hi> Teſtament; That <hi>the Government ſhould be upon his Shoulders,</hi> and the like; and alſo from what is ſaid of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> in the <hi>New.</hi> That <note n="(b)" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> x. 38. <hi>Hebr.</hi> iii. 1. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> ii. 25. <hi>Mat.</hi> xxviii. 18. Proprie Epiſcopus Dominus Jeſus eſt. <hi>Origen</hi> on <hi>Mat.</hi> xxiv.</note> 
               <hi>God Annointed him with the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> and as it were Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated him to be <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Paſtour, and the great Apoſtle and High Prieſt of our Profeſſion, and Biſhop of our Souls, and that he had all Power both in Heaven and in Earth:</hi> and that he did in his own Perſon Rule and Govern, make Laws and conſtitute Governours, and not only did he
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:61584:6"/>declare Gods Will to Mankind, but did alſo take order that ſuch Perſons ſhould be admitted into that his Society by <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> as were willing to ſubmit to the Rules and Conſtitutions of it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That <hi>Our Saviour</hi> committed the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this Society, to thoſe who in the <hi>Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſts</hi> are call'd <hi>Apoſtles.</hi> This appears from the tenour of the Commiſſion which he gave them, when he breathed on them the <note n="(c)" place="bottom">
                  <hi>John</hi> xx. 21, 22.</note> 
               <hi>Holy Ghoſt. As my Father ſent me, ſo ſend I you. Whoſeſoever ſins ye remit they are remitted unto them, and whoſeſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Sins ye retain, they are retained.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The ſame Authority which was given to the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> to Govern this Society (excepting thoſe attendants of <hi>Gifts,</hi> as of Tongues, doing Miracles, and the like Extraordinary Helps and Supplies, which the Neceſſity of the Primitive Church requir'd, till it <hi>came in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Faith unto a perfect Man, unto the meaſure of the ſtature of the fulneſs of Chriſt, as St.</hi> Paul <hi>expreſſes it</hi>) was for ever to continue to their Succeſſors.</p>
            <p>This appears from the very Nature and Deſign of that Government which <hi>Chriſt</hi> appointed; it being ſo abſolutely neceſſary to the preſervation <note n="(d)" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> iv.</note>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:61584:7"/>of his Society, and conſequently of his Religion, that ſuch a Society could not ſubſiſt without it; and therefore as neceſſary to continue that Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety, as firſt to form it. Some will think more neceſſary in ſucceding Ages, than at that time, when our Saviour's Miracles were ſo freſh in their remembrance; their Devotion ſo new, and their Zeal ſo warm and vigorous. We likewiſe find this plainly intimated in the Commiſſion which <hi>Chriſt</hi> gave his <hi>Apoſtles.</hi> 
               <note n="(e)" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> xxviii. 18, 20.</note> 
               <hi>Go and teach;</hi> or make Diſciples in <hi>all Nations, and lo I am with you alway even unto the end of the World.</hi> Now they themſelves were not to live ſo long, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this ſpecial Preſence and Aſſiſtance, muſt be underſtood to have been promiſed to their Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors alſo.</p>
            <p>Farther, <hi>Chriſt ſent them as his Father ſent him;</hi> that is, with ſuch Authority to Ordain others, and to Inſtitute Eccleſiaſtical Diſcipline, and ſo to make Succeſſors, and to communicate to them of that Spirit, which he breathed on them, as <hi>Moſes</hi> did to <hi>Joſhua,</hi> 
               <note n="(f)" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> xxxiv. 9.</note> the <hi>Spirit of Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> by <hi>laying their hands</hi> upon them. And hence it was that St. <hi>Paul</hi> told the <hi>Biſhops of Aſia,</hi> upon whom he had lay'd his hands, when upon his Summons They met him at <hi>Miletus,</hi> 
               <note n="(g)" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> xx. 28.</note> That
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:61584:7"/>the <hi>Holy Ghoſt had made them Overſeers,</hi> or Biſhops, <hi>over the Church of God.</hi> I may add, that all Diſputers in this Cauſe, and all Pretenders to different Forms of <hi>Church-Government,</hi> do Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge ſome Form to be always neceſſary, and conſequently Authority to Rule and Govern, for ever to reſide in ſome Perſons or other.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That <hi>Biſhops,</hi> be the true extent of their Authority what it will, are declar'd to be in Scripture, and were look'd upon in the firſt Ages (h) of the <hi>Church,</hi> as Succeſſors to the <hi>Apoſtles;</hi> and ſo Authoriz'd by <hi>Chriſt</hi> to Govern this Society.</p>
            <p>Thus far we have but little Controverſie with the main Oppoſers of <hi>Epiſcopacy.</hi> For they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not deny but that our <hi>Biſhops</hi> are <hi>Presbyters,</hi> and therefore if, (as they will have it) <hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> were the Antient <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and are Succeſſors to the Apoſtles, our <hi>Biſhops</hi> upon that account are ſo. If therefore we be ſatisfied that <hi>Our Saviour</hi> gave ſome Power and Authority to his <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> with a deſign that They ſhould leave it to others, to be tranſmitted through all Ages <note n="(h)" place="bottom">St. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> Epiſt. 75. p. 225. Edit. <hi>Oxon.</hi> Poteſtas pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum remittendorum Apoſtolis data eſt, &amp; Eccleſiis quas illi à Chriſto miſſi Conſtituerunt, &amp; Epiſcopis qui eis Ordinatione Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cariâ ſucceſſerunt.</note>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:61584:8"/>ſucceſſively, to ſome fit perſons, for the Exigen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of the <hi>Church;</hi> and that our <hi>Biſhops</hi> are Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors to thoſe <hi>Apoſtles</hi> (which one Party of our <hi>Churches</hi> Adverſaries are obliged to own, by virtue of their being <hi>Presbyters;</hi> and which the other have no pretence to deny here in <hi>Ireland,</hi> whatever Fables <note n="(i)" place="bottom">For Confutation of which, See <hi>Maſon's Vindiciae Eccleſiae Anglicanae,</hi> Primate <hi>Bramhali</hi>'s Works, and the Second Part of Dr. <hi>Burnet</hi>'s <hi>Hiſtory of the Reformation.</hi>
               </note> they have invented, to diſparage the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Conſecrations; we being able to prove, That our preſent <hi>Biſhops</hi> of <hi>Ireland</hi> were Conſecrated by <note n="(k)" place="bottom">For Inſtance. His Grace the Moſt-Reverend Father in God, <hi>Michael Boyle,</hi> the preſent Lord Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Armagh,</hi> and Primate of all <hi>Ireland;</hi> together with Dr. <hi>Margetſon,</hi> the Late Primate of <hi>Ireland:</hi> the truly Learned and Pious Dr. <hi>John Parker,</hi> late Lord Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Dublin,</hi> Dr. <hi>Pullen,</hi> then Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Tuam,</hi> and the preſent Lord Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Caſhell,</hi> and Seven other Biſhops who died ſince, were Conſecrated <hi>Jan.</hi> 27. 1660. By Dr. <hi>John Bramhall,</hi> Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Armagh,</hi> who was Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated <hi>May,</hi> 26. 1634. by Primate <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher,</hi> who was Conſecrated <hi>Anno</hi> 1621. by Primate <hi>Hampton,</hi> who was Conſecrated <hi>May,</hi> 5. 1613. by Dr. <hi>Thomas Jones,</hi> who was Conſecrated, by <hi>Adam Loſtus,</hi> Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Dublin,</hi> 12. <hi>May,</hi> 1584. who was Conſecrated by <hi>Hugh Curwin, Anno</hi> 1562. who was Conſecrated Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Dublin, Septemb.</hi> 8. 1555. being the Third Year of Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> together with <hi>James Turberville</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Exceter,</hi> and <hi>William Glin,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Bangor:</hi> This appears out of our Records, and by this may any of the preſent Lords Biſhops of <hi>Ireland,</hi> Juſtifie their Conſecration.</note> ſuch <hi>Biſhops,</hi> as receiv'd their Conſecration from other Conſecrated
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:61584:8"/>
               <hi>Biſhops;</hi> and ſo on to before the <hi>Reformation;</hi> from Records never in the leaſt queſtion'd or ſuſpected) we muſt Acknowledge that what Authority our preſent <hi>Biſhops</hi> have, They have from <hi>Chriſt Jeſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The way being thus far clear'd, before I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to the main thing behind, to wit; To de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate, that Biſhops are a diſtinct Order from and above <hi>Presbyters,</hi> by that Authority They have receiv'd from <hi>Chriſt,</hi> I ſhall deduce ſome few Corollaries from what has been ſaid, ſuch as:</p>
            <p n="1">1. 'Tis evident from hence, That when the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> Ordained <hi>Biſhops,</hi> they did it by Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority given them by our <hi>Saviour;</hi> and not only in purſuance of a <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Cuſtom of creating <hi>Elders,</hi> which the famous Mr. <hi>Selden</hi> ſo much contends <note n="(l)" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Selden</hi> de Synedriis, <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Cap.</hi> 14.</note> for. Had they not done it upon an Account peculiar to <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> when a <hi>Jew,</hi> and a moſt violent Perſecutor of <hi>Chriſts Church,</hi> had had as full Authority to make <hi>Biſhops</hi> as when a <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> and muſt have deriv'd it not from the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> (as he conſtantly Affirms) but from his Maſter <hi>Gamaliel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Hence it follows, That <hi>Biſhops</hi> have not
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:61584:9"/>their Authority from the Civil Magiſtrate. There is a great difference between the deſignation of a Perſon to an Office, and the giving him Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in it. Thus a <hi>Mayor</hi> of a Corporation is Choſen by the <hi>Burgeſſes</hi> of it, but receives his Authority from the <hi>King</hi> alone; and ſo in many other inſtances. And therefore this Aſſertion of ours, cannot be ſuſpected as any way prejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial to our Princes Antient Right of Electing <hi>Biſhops.</hi> The <hi>Church</hi> is a Society, and Body Politick diſtinct from that of the <hi>Common-wealth;</hi> which appears from hence, That it did ſubſiſt when ſeparated from, and perſecuted by all Civil-Powers; it is founded upon Principles different from the Law of Nature, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Notions of Mankind, and ſettled by Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Poſitive Laws; and conſequently the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of it muſt be proportionable. And they who reſolve to hold the contrary Opinion, may take its Foundation along with it, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the <hi>Goſpel</hi> it ſelf to be no Law, but as Enacted by the <hi>Civil Magiſtrate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. We may hence infer, that all other <hi>Biſhops</hi> are not merely Subſtitutes of the <hi>Biſhop of</hi> Rome, and that he in the Right of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> is not the <hi>Only Biſhop,</hi> who hath his Authority from <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſo that all muſt receive theirs from him. This was with much Vehemence and equal Applauſe,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:61584:9"/>defended in the <note n="(m)" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Hiſt. Council of</hi> Trent, <hi>Lib.</hi> 7. <hi>pag.</hi> 574. of the laſt Edition. <hi>Engl.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Trent,</hi> by Father <hi>Laynez,</hi> General of the <hi>Jeſuits:</hi> and <hi>Friar Simon</hi> a <hi>Florentine,</hi> did there likewiſe maintain, That the Inſtitution of <hi>Biſhops</hi> in the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> was only Perſonal, and ended with them. But this (as the good <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Paris</hi> then ſaid) is a Novel Doctrine; firſt invented by <hi>Cajetane</hi> to gain a <hi>Cardinalſhip;</hi> and as ſuch was Cenſured by the Doctors of the <hi>Sorbonne,</hi> and <hi>Richerius</hi> a <note n="(n)" place="bottom">Richerius. Cap. <hi>10.</hi> Sect. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Sorbonne Doctor,</hi> in his <hi>Hiſtory of General Councills,</hi> lately Printed; has made it out, That in Antient Times the very <hi>Italian Biſhops</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, did ſubſcribe <hi>Biſhops, Dei Gratia, without any mention of the Pope, or Apoſtolick See.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. We may likewiſe hence conclude, That <hi>Biſhops</hi> have not, nor ought to have their Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority from the People. That they had, in the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> days, was held by Mr. <hi>Hobbes;</hi> 
               <note n="(o)" place="bottom">Leviathan. Cap. <hi>22.</hi>
               </note> and he ſays, 'Tis ſo declar'd in Scripture. But 'tis plain, that he makes it the ſame thing, to Elect and to Ordain, which the <note n="(p)" place="bottom">Acts <hi>vi. 5. The whole Multitude Choſe</hi> Stephen <hi>and</hi> Philip, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Verſ. <hi>6.</hi> Whom they ſet before the Apoſtles, who, when they had Prayed, lay'd their Hands on them.</note> 
               <hi>Scriptures</hi> make very different. As to what relates to the People,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:61584:10"/>it does indeed appear from Antiquity; that They were ſomewhat concern'd in the Election of <hi>Biſhops;</hi> 
               <note n="(q)" place="bottom">Of this matter ſee a full and ſatisfactory Account, in the <hi>Hiſtory of the preſent Separation,</hi> by the Worthy and moſt Learned Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet,</hi> Part 3. Sect. 24.25.</note> but 'twas only by way of Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation, and that St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Rule might be the better obſerv'd, <hi>That a Biſhop be Blameleſs, and of Good Report.</hi> And that they were of <hi>Good Report</hi> the People could beſt teſtifie. But this occaſion'd many diſturbances, ſo that Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Magiſtrates were forced ſometimes to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſe, and at laſt upon prudent Conſiderations 'twas quite diſ-uſed.</p>
            <p>Having ſetled theſe matters, I come now to prove, that <hi>Biſhops</hi> by vertue of this Authority which they have from <hi>Chriſt,</hi> are above <hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</hi> I muſt deſire to be excuſed that I do not make the Enquiry, <hi>Whether Biſhops be of a diſtinct Order from that of Presbyters, Jure Divino</hi> or not. Which by the Advantage of Ambiguous expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, made uſe of by ſome unwarily, by others on purpoſe, and by the motives of Intereſt and Envy, has been made the ſubject of much diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute, and of many Books in this laſt Age. This I have deſignedly declin'd medling with. For
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:61584:10"/>unleſs we be willing Eternally to wrangle and diſpute, and to make the Controverſy to laſt as long as the Order it ſelf, <hi>even to the end of the World;</hi> We muſt ſtate the Queſtion plainly, and after ſome ſort, that we may find a clear deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of it ſome way or other. And I know none more fair than this: <hi>Whether the Apoſtles before their Martyrdoms committed the Authority, which Chriſt gave them of Governing his Church, and the inferior Officers of it, and of Ordaining others in every Church to ſingle Perſons, or to ſeveral in Conjunction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To determine this, Let us firſt conſult the <hi>Holy Scriptures.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We find that the firſt Succeſſor to any of the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> who was made by them, was <hi>Matthias;</hi> who when <hi>Judas-</hi> had fallen away, though he was a Diſciple, by the direction of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> 
               <note n="(r)" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> i.</note> was aſſm'd to a higher de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, to the dignity of an <hi>Apoſtle.</hi> 
               <note n="(s)" place="bottom">The Apoſtles were above the 70 Diſciples. <hi>Philip</hi> did Preach, Baptiſe, did Miracles, and Converted the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maritans,</hi> but his Converts did not receive the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> till that St. <hi>Peter</hi> and St. <hi>John,</hi> came down from <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and laid their hands upon them. <hi>Acts.</hi> viii. 14.15. And that <hi>Matthias</hi> before he was made Succeſſor to <hi>Judas,</hi> was one of the 70. Diſciples. Vid. <hi>Euſebii Hiſt. Eccl. Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Cap.</hi> 12.</note> St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſays, <hi>To take</hi> Judas <hi>his Biſhoprick.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:61584:11"/>
            <p>We find St. <hi>James</hi> (who was not <note n="(t)" place="bottom">That <hi>James</hi> the Brother of our Lord was not one of the Twelve, <hi>Valeſius</hi> ſhews at large, in his Notes on the ſame Chapter. <hi>Not. Pag.</hi> 20.</note> of the Twelve, and whom all <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtonias</hi> reckon) <hi>Biſhop of Hieruſalem,</hi> that he reſided conſtantly there, and that any matter of impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance which hapned, was communicated unto him. That the <hi>Presbyters</hi> attended on him: that when St. <hi>Peter</hi> was deliver'd out of Priſon by an Angel, he bade them whom he firſt met, <note n="(u)" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> xii. 17.</note> 
               <hi>to go and ſhew thoſe things unto</hi> James, <hi>and unto the Brethren;</hi> and that St. <hi>Paul,</hi> as ſoon <note n="(w)" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> xxi. 18.</note> as he came to <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> after his <hi>Fourteen</hi> Years Preaching to the <hi>Gentiles, went in unto</hi> James, <hi>and all the Elders were preſent.</hi> Though the <hi>Presbyters</hi> were all there, he made his Application in a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular manner to St. <hi>James.</hi> And in the Firſt <hi>Council</hi> held there upon occaſion of a Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie about keeping the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> St. <hi>James</hi> determin'd as one in Authority, in theſe words: <note n="(x)" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Acts.</hi> xv. 19.</note> 
               <hi>Wherefore my Sentence is.</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted his Authority at <hi>Epheſus</hi> to <hi>Timothy;</hi> we find him give him in Charge, <hi>That he ſhould not receive an Accuſation againſt a Presbyters, but</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd <hi>by two or three witneſſes,</hi> 
               <note n="(y)" place="bottom">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> v. 19, 20.</note> 
               <hi>and him
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:61584:11"/>that ſinned, to Rebuke before all, that others alſo might fear.</hi> So by his Place we ſee that he might receive an Accuſation, and ſummon Witneſſes before him, and Examine them, and give Sentence againſt <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters,</hi> which he could not have done, had they been his Equals. Beſides, he was charged with a ſolemn adjuration <note n="(z)" place="bottom">Verſ. 21.</note> 
               <hi>before God and the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and the Elect Angels,</hi> to do theſe things <hi>without Partiality;</hi> which ſhews that by his Authority he was able to ſhew fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to ſome <hi>Presbyters</hi> above others, and that his Partiality would have been of great Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence. The ſame St. <hi>Paul</hi> made <hi>Titus Metro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politan</hi> of <hi>Creet,</hi> gave him Authority <note n="(a)" place="bottom">1 <hi>Titus,</hi> v.</note> To <hi>Ordain Elders in every City.</hi> And as to what cencerns the reſt of the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> we may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leive They endeavour'd that there ſhould be Uniformity in all <hi>Churches,</hi> which 'tis plain <note n="(b)" place="bottom">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> vii. 17. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> xiv. 33.</note> St. <hi>Paul</hi> labour'd much after: and Uniformity could not be, had they inſtituted different Forms of Government in them.</p>
            <p>But no conſidering Perſon will think it ſtrange, that the particular Form of Government is not more expreſly deſcribed in the Relation we have in thoſe Sacred Books, of what was done by
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:61584:12"/>the Apoſtles immediately after our <hi>Saviours</hi> Aſcenſion. They could not of a ſudden ſettle all matters; nor was it neceſſary that They ſhould appoint Succeſſors long before they were to leave them. Beſides, the Account which we have of what they did, is very ſhort. St. <hi>Luke</hi> was the only Perſon who Compos'd and left to Poſterity, Commentaries o their Acts. In them we find little of St. <hi>Peter;</hi> but what was tranſacted within a Year or two after his Maſters <hi>Aſcenſion;</hi> little of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> but his Converſion, and what St. <hi>Luke</hi> ſaw him do in his ſeveral journeys; leſs of any other of the Apoſtles. And as to St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Epiſtles, they do rather ſuppoſe the then Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment (whatever it was) ſufficiently known, than undertake to deſcribe it. And after all thoſe Books were finiſh'd, we have reaſon to believe, that the <hi>Church</hi> being ſo very much enlarged by the Acceſſion of New Converts, that they made their form of Government more exact than before Comported with the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of Affairs.</p>
            <p>However, One thing, we find in the <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations,</hi> which ſeems plain enough in this matter. Our <hi>Saviour</hi> Commanded St. <hi>John</hi> to write to the <hi>Angels</hi> of the Seven <hi>Churches</hi> of <hi>Aſia:</hi> That it was not to the Seven <hi>Churches</hi> themſelves, is evident from his Saving, <hi>That</hi> the ſeven <hi>Churches</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:61584:12"/>were the <hi>Seven Candleſticks,</hi> but the <hi>Seven Stars</hi> 
               <note n="(c)" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> i. 20. St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſays, by the <hi>Angel</hi> is meant <hi>Praepo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitus Eccleſiae.</hi> St. <hi>Hierom, Angeli Eccleſiis Praeſidentes.</hi> This Senſe is allow'd by <hi>Bullinger</hi> and <hi>Beza.</hi>
               </note> were <hi>the ſeven Angels,</hi> which did ſhine in them. That the <hi>Angel</hi> of each of thoſe <hi>Churches</hi> was not a Synod of <hi>Presbyters,</hi> but a <hi>Single Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> appears from this, that the Reproofs and Charges given there, are Perſonal. We cannot ſay, for inſtance, that all the Elders of the <note n="(d)" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> xx. 17, 18.</note> 
               <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> (where St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſettled many) could agree in all thoſe Qualifications and Defects mentioned by St. <hi>John:</hi> from whence it follows, that each of thoſe <hi>Churches</hi> in St. <hi>John</hi>'s days was Governed by <hi>Single Perſons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But tho' there be ſome who will have nothing eſteemed of momen in this Concern, but what is found in <hi>Scripture,</hi> or in ſome Syſtem of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity; yet I hope we may be allowed to make recourſe to Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtory. For we are not to ſeek in the <hi>Scriptures</hi> for what was done after that they were written; and the Fathers who were the Succeſſors of the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> can beſt tell what they who were next before them, did, To ſhew the unreaſonableneſs of the contrary Opinion, I ſhall propoſe a like Caſe. If a Queſtion were now made, how <hi>Alexander</hi> the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:61584:13"/>Great his Empire was diſpoſed of after his Death, and any one would take upon him to dictate with great Confidence, That we ought not to conſult <hi>Diodorus Siculus, Plutarch</hi> and others, who wrote of thoſe Tranſactions, but to apply our ſelves wholly to <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> Politicks, (or which is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed much nearer to the prudent Advice of ſome of our <hi>Anti-Epiſcopal</hi> writers) to take the words of ſome now alive; and to ſend for certain Sober, Good, Able Men; to whom they can recommend us, who perhaps have never much troubled themſelves with that uſeleſs Study of <hi>Hiſtory;</hi> but yet having profoundly ſtudied Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticks, can from their own Models and Principles beſt inform us, how thoſe matters went then; we ſhould, I preſume, beg their Pardon, and upon the very ſame grounds we muſt ſo now, and addreſs our ſelves to Antiquity for a Reſolution.</p>
            <p>Now we cannot find one word in <hi>Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical Hiſtory,</hi> (of which it is not improbable that they are well aware) that from the days of the very <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> any <hi>Church</hi> was otherwiſe Governed than by a <hi>Single Perſon,</hi> till after the beginning of the Sixteenth <hi>Century.</hi> But it would not be proper here to proſecute this matter largely, and therefore I ſhall only propoſe a few inſtances out of the moſt early Chriſtian Writers.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:61584:13"/>
            <p>The eldeſt of the Fathers we have is <hi>Clemens Romanus;</hi> and he in his excellent <hi>Epiſtle</hi> to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> ſhews plainly that he was of Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion; that, as it was actually in his Time, the Apoſtles themſelves did by Divine Inſpiration continue a Government, in which <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Presbyters</hi> were no leſs diſtinguiſhed than they are now. I cannot ſtay to conſider what is weakly Objected out of him, but muſt refer to others, particularly to the two Learned An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notators upon him; and to the Worthy and Learned Defender <note n="(e)" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Beveridge, Codex Can. Vindic. Cap. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> of the <hi>Codex Canonum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>St. <hi>Ignatius</hi> the Martyr, who Lived with the Apoſtles, and was afterwards <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Antioch</hi> himſelf, in many places of his Epiſtles, ſhews that the <hi>Church</hi> was Governed by <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and that he means by a Biſhop <note n="(f)" place="bottom">That St. <hi>Ignatius</hi> does not term the Order of <hi>Biſhops</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> as <hi>Rivet</hi> and <hi>Salmaſius</hi> will have it. See Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi>'s <hi>Diſſert. Pag.</hi> 77.</note> the ſame that we do. And indeed his Teſtimony in this Controverſie, is ſo full and poſitive, that they who deſire that what he Affirms ſhould not be true, and yet pretend ſome Reſpect for ſo Apoſtolick a man, have no ſhift, but to deny that theſe Epiſtles are Genuine. But that they are, has
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:61584:14"/>been as fully demonſtrated, as any thing of that nature can poſſibly be, formerly by ſeveral other worthy Perſons, particularly by that Prodigie of Learning and Piety, the moſt Excellent <hi>Primate <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher,</hi> a Perſon one would think, ſufficient to reconcile Men, who were Lovers of either, to that Order; and ſince by a Reverend and Learned Prelate <note n="(g)" place="bottom">The Reverend Biſhop of <hi>Cheſter.</hi>
               </note> now Living, in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That <hi>Biſhops</hi> were above <hi>Presbyters</hi> in the Second <hi>Century,</hi> is expreſly Aſſerted by <note n="(h)" place="bottom">Clemens Alexandr. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Lib. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>12.</hi> pag. <hi>264.</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>More clearly,</hi> Stromat. Lib. <hi>6.</hi> Pag. <hi>667.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus,</hi> by <note n="(i)" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Orig.</hi> in <hi>Hieremiam Homil.</hi> 11. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> (for he was then himſelf a Presbyter) <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. By whom undoubredly is meant the Biſhop, and it plainly ſhews, That he was above the Presbyters. <hi>Edit. Huet. Rothomag. Anno</hi> 1668. <hi>Pag.</hi> 114. <hi>Huetius</hi> gueſſes that <hi>Origen</hi> underſtands either <hi>Theoctiſtus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Caeſarea,</hi> or <hi>Babylas</hi> Patriarch of <hi>Antioch. Obſervat. Pag.</hi> 14. <hi>Origen</hi> likewiſe on <hi>Mat. Ch.</hi> xix. <hi>Pag.</hi> 363. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. On <hi>Cap.</hi> 21. <hi>pag.</hi> 442. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Origen,</hi> and <note n="(k)" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Tertullian de Baptiſmo. cap.</hi> 17. Dandi quidem habet jus Summus Sacerdos, qui eſt Epiſcopus; dehinc Presbyteri &amp; Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coni, non tamen ſine Epiſcopi Auctoritate, propter Eccleſiae Honorem, quo ſalvo, ſalva pax eſt.</note> 
               <hi>Tertullian.</hi> Of <hi>Heraclas,</hi> who was afterwards
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:61584:14"/>
               <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Alexandria, Origen</hi> 
               <note n="(l)" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Apud</hi> Euſeb. Hiſt. Eccl. Lib. <hi>6.</hi> Cap. <hi>19.</hi> Pag. <hi>180. Edit.</hi> Paris. Anno <hi>1678.</hi>
               </note> teſtifies, That he was firſt a <hi>Presbyter</hi> of the ſame <hi>Church.</hi> That <hi>Irenaeus</hi> was firſt a <hi>Presbyter,</hi> afterwards <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Lions,</hi> appears from <hi>Euſebius,</hi> 
               <note n="(m)" place="bottom">Euſeb. Hiſt. Lib. <hi>5.</hi> Cap. <hi>4.</hi> &amp; <hi>5.</hi> Hi ron. in Catal. Scriptor. Eccl. ad Script. <hi>64. ſpeaking of</hi> Origen. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and St. <hi>Hierom: Dionyſius Alexandrinus,</hi> in an Epiſtle to <hi>Dionyſius Romanus,</hi> ſhews that he was then a <hi>Presbyter;</hi> afterwards <hi>Euſebius</hi> and St. <hi>Hierom</hi> inform us, <note n="(n)" place="bottom">Euſeb. Lib. <hi>7.</hi> Cap. <hi>7.</hi> &amp; Hieron, in Gatal. Script. <hi>45.</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> That he was a <hi>Biſhop. Irenaeus,</hi> and <hi>Euſebius, Socrates,</hi> and <hi>Theodoret,</hi> do furniſh us with Catalogues of the <hi>Biſhops</hi> in their reſpective Sees, from the very Time of the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> to their days. And St. <hi>Hierom</hi> ſays, <note n="(o)" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Hieron. in Epiſt. ad Evagrium quae incrpit, Legimus in Iſaiah.</hi> 'Tis his Eighty Fifth Epiſtle. Nam &amp; Alexandriae à Marco Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtâ uſque ad Heraclam &amp; Dionyſium Epiſcopos, Presbyteri ſemper unum ex ſe electum in excelſiori gradu collocatum, Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copum nominabant.</note> That from the time of St. <hi>Mark</hi> there was a <hi>Biſhop</hi> always above <hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> in the Church of <hi>Alexandria.</hi> And all this is ſo very clear, that none were they not moſt perverſely biaſs'd by Prejudice or Intereſt, if they be acquainted with Antiquity, would queſtion it.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:61584:15"/>
            <p>The firſt Man that ever we can hear of, who did oppoſe the Superiority of <hi>Biſhops</hi> above <hi>Presbyters,</hi> was <hi>Aerius,</hi> almoſt 330 Years after our Saviour, a very Proud, Humorſome Man, who becauſe he could not obtain a <hi>Biſhoprick</hi> which he aimed at, as <hi>Epiphanius</hi> informs us, <note n="(p)" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Epiphanii, Haereſs.</hi> 56. <hi>ſeu utalii,</hi> 75. Speaking of <hi>Aerius.</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Afterwards <hi>Euſtathius</hi> made him a <hi>Presbyter,</hi> and Maſter in the Hoſpital in <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ntus;</hi> but for all this <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. And he after much ſhew of diſcontent, quitted the Place, and led many poor people after him, telling them that a <hi>Presbyters</hi> was as good as a Biſhop. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> he reſolv'd that a <hi>Biſhop</hi> was not above a <hi>Presbyter;</hi> and for his he was by the good Men of thoſe days, condemn'd of Hereſie, and therefore we cannot but ſuſpect that there is a little too much aſſurance in the Men of our Times, who deſire to be thought moſt Pure and Orthodox, and yet will undertake againſt the whole Church of God, for many hundreds of Years, to defend a Notorious, Infamous Heretick; a Heretick who had no Sober Man in thoſe Ages to Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance him. For as for <hi>Medina,</hi> who ſays, That St. <hi>Hierome, Sedulius</hi> and others, were of his Hereſie, the Moſt Learned Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Spalato,</hi> do's
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:61584:15"/>prove him <note n="(q)" place="bottom">In his Second Book <hi>De Republ. Eceleſ. cap.</hi> 3. Of the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between the Opinions of St. <hi>Hierons</hi> and <hi>Aerius,</hi> See the Learned <hi>John Forbes,</hi> his <hi>Irenicum. Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 11.</note> to be very impudent for ſaying ſo.</p>
            <p>But all this and much more of this nature makes but little with ſome, in this Cauſe. For when by Learned Men it was demonſtrated, That <hi>Biſhops</hi> were above <hi>Presbyters,</hi> in the very Firſt and Pureſt Ages of the Church; They whoſe Paſſions or Intereſts had render'd them Enemies to that Order, made this Reply. <hi>That</hi> Diotre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phes <hi>ſought the Preheminence in the</hi> Apoſtles <hi>times, and the Myſtery of Iniquity did then begin to work.</hi> Among others, this is the Anſwer of a <hi>Presbyter</hi> of great Fame and Repute among his Followers, who were deeply Engag'd in the Late Troubles, <hi>Alezander Henderſon,</hi> 
               <note n="(r)" place="bottom">Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſon<hi>'s Firſt Paper.</hi> Pag. <hi>157. Of the Edit.</hi> Anno <hi>1649. and his Second Paper,</hi> Pag. <hi>170.</hi> I wind together <hi>Diotrephes</hi> and the Myſtery of Iniquity, the one as an Old Example of Church-Ambition, which was alſo too palpable in the Apoſtle themſelves, and the other as a Cover of Ambition, afterwards diſcovered; which two brought forth the great Myſtery of the Papacy at laſt.</note> in a Letter to the Late <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Bleſſed Memory;</hi> and in his <hi>Firſt Paper,</hi> he had the modeſty to call our <hi>Biſhops,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:61584:16"/>The</hi> 
               <note n="(s)" place="bottom">
                  <hi>His Firſt Paper.</hi> Pag. <hi>154.</hi> It is too well known, That the Reformation of <hi>Hen. VIII.</hi> was moſt imperfect in the Eſſentials of Doctrin, Worſhip and Government; and although it proceeded by ſome degrees afterwards, yet the Government was never Reformed, the Head was Changed, <hi>Dominus non Dominium;</hi> and the whole Limbs of the Antichriſtian Hierarchy retained, upon what Snares and Temptations of Avarice and Ambition, the great Enchanters of the Clergie, I need not expreſs.</note> 
               <hi>Limbs of the Antichriſtian Hierarchie.</hi> I ſhall not poſitively Charge him with what a Reverend Divine, who had been a Member of the <hi>Synod</hi> of <hi>Dort,</hi> tells us <note n="(t)" place="bottom">Biſhop <hi>Hall;</hi> Of Epiſcopacy. <hi>Pag.</hi> 52.</note> was Reported of him, That when he was Moderator of that famous <hi>Aſſembly at</hi> Glaſgow, <note n="(u)" place="bottom">See the Large Declaration about the Troubles in <hi>Scotland. Pag.</hi> 237.</note> he ſaid, That <hi>St.</hi> Paul <hi>himſelf, by Appointing Biſhops, was a Worker in that Myſtery of Iniquity.</hi> But 'twas not long after that this Anſwer was Applauded, That the <hi>Socinians, Independents,</hi> and <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> took confidence from he Example, and termed the Myſtery of the <hi>Holy Trinity,</hi> the Power of inflicting Eccleſiaſtical Cenſures, and the Baptizing of Infants, <hi>The Myſtery o Iniquity.</hi> And truly ſome Learned Men think that there cannot be more ſaid for the Baptizing of Infants, nay for the Cannon of the Scripture, and for the Obſervation of the Lord's Day it ſelf, than for Epiſcopacy.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:61584:16"/>
            <p>However, ſhall we think that our Saviour would be ſo unkind to his Church, as to deliver it up wholly to the Management of <hi>Antichriſt</hi> for fifteen hundred years together? Nay, if <hi>Biſhops</hi> becauſe <hi>Biſhops,</hi> muſt be <hi>Antichriſts,</hi> how can we avoid reckoning St. <hi>James</hi> himſelf, the <hi>Brother of our Lord,</hi> the <hi>Antichriſt</hi> of <hi>Jeruſalem, Timothy</hi> the <hi>Antichriſt</hi> of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> of <hi>Creet?</hi> And St. <hi>John</hi> ſhould not have directed his Epiſtles to the <hi>Seven Angels,</hi> but in our [<hi>New Stile</hi>] to <hi>the Seven Antichriſts</hi> of the <hi>Churches</hi> of <hi>Aſia.</hi> Shall we think that <hi>Chriſt's Apoſtles</hi> themſelves, who Lived to See, and to Eſtabliſh <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> as to the Eſſential Parts of it, as it now ſtands, would betray his <hi>Church</hi> into the hands of <hi>Antichriſt;</hi> and help to exalt the <hi>Man of Sin?</hi> and that many of the moſt Godly and Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Servants of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> the Bleſſed Martyrs of the <hi>Primitive Church,</hi> would be themſelves <hi>Limbs of Antichriſt,</hi> and rejoyce in him? far be it from us to entertain ſuch horrid Imaginations.</p>
            <p>But to take no farther Notice of odious Terms and ill Language. Did <hi>Chriſt's Apoſtles</hi> behave themſelves Unfaithfully in their Charge, and when they had Converted Perſons enough to make a <hi>Church,</hi> did they Eſtabliſh any other Form of Government than what they had receiv'd Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion from their Maſter to Eſtabliſh, and which
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:61584:17"/>was to Endure to <hi>the End of the World?</hi> all which Time, we ſee he has promiſed his ſpecial Preſence and Aſſiſtance, to their Legal Succeſſors.</p>
            <p>And as to thoſe who ſucceeded the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> ſhall we ſuſpect that ſuch good Men, that Men who died for the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> durſt preſume to ſet up a Government contrary to it; and ſo unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly agree in ſo wicked a Contrivance? They were doubtleſs, Holy, Conſcientious, and Morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied Perſons, very Humble and Devout; and therefore we cannot honeſtly ſay, (as ſome would have the firſt deviſers of <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> to have been) That they were Covetous, Proud, Ambitious, Tyrannical, and Uſurpers. Was it Honour, Riches, State and Grandeur, that thoſe Humble, Patient Men, who were always under Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, could be Corrupted and Allured with, in thoſe Days when, (as the famous <hi>Petrus de Marca,</hi> upon occaſion <note n="(w)" place="bottom">Pet. de Marc. de Concord. Tom. <hi>2.</hi> Pag. <hi>81.</hi> Sect. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> of Pope <hi>Leo</hi> his Letter to <hi>Anaſtaſius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Theſſalonica,</hi> truly obſerves) That <hi>Epiſcopatus erat veluti gradus quidam ad crudeliſſima ſupplicia,</hi> a Biſhoprick intituled the Poſſeſſour only to the Priviledge of being more Barbarouſly Tormented than othes? Nay, after that Age, the Biſhops themſelves were ſo good
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:61584:17"/>Men, ſo excellent, <note n="(x)" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Calvin</hi>'s <hi>Inſtit.</hi> Printed at <hi>Geneva;</hi> 1550. <hi>cap.</hi> 8. <hi>Sect.</hi> 53.</note> that <hi>Calvin</hi> ſays (and we may venture to take his word when he ſpeaks well of any of that Order) that a bad Biſhop would have been eſteemed <hi>inſtar portenti,</hi> as a ſtrange, prodigious thing! ſhall we ſuppoſe that theſe Men would be ſo abominably ungrateful to their Lord and Saviour, as moſt Sacrilegiouſly to violate his own Inſtitution, and ſo injurious to their Brethren, as to rob them of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority given them by their <hi>Maſter?</hi> and yet if we hold either <hi>Presbytery,</hi> or any other way than what they then uſed, to be of <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution; we muſt conclude theſe Martyrs, theſe Holy, Devout, Self-denying Men, to have been ſo Covetous, ſo Falſe, ſo Ambitious, ſuch Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants, ſuch Uſurpers. One might tremble to think that to maintain a New Conceit, and the Credit of ſome Popular Men among us in a wicked degenerate Age, we ſhould labour to prove thoſe Worthies, the Baſeſt, Falſeſt Villains, that ever lived among Men.</p>
            <p>But if they were ſo, could they have Agreed all the World over in this <hi>Knavery,</hi> (for it ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits not of a ſofter expreſſion) were all the reſt ſo tame as to ſubmit to it? And why did not
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:61584:18"/>the <hi>Presbyters then,</hi> as ſome of ours did of late, riſe up againſt them and ſay they were <hi>Anti-Chriſtian?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon the whole, we ſee that for a <hi>Biſhop</hi> to be above the <hi>Presbyters</hi> is not late Uſurpation, but Practis'd in the Pureſt, in all the Ages of the <hi>Chriſtian Church;</hi> not invented by <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> nor part of the <hi>Myſtery of Iniquity,</hi> but an <hi>Apoſtolick</hi> Conſtitution, conformable to our <hi>Saviour</hi>'s own. And who can ſhew a better Title to any Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges or Eſtates upon Earth, than a Poſſeſſion of above <hi>Sixteen Hundred</hi> Years, without the leaſt Fraud or Violence at the beginning? This therefore being manifeſt, that in the Ages im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately following the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> the <hi>Churches</hi> were Govern'd by <hi>Single Perſons,</hi> who pretended to derive their Authority from them; and that we have all the reaſon imaginable to believe, that they would not, nay that they could not, have pretended ſo, had it been falſe: we may ſafely conclude, That they had, and conſequently that they who are their Legal Succeſſors, now have their Authority from the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and ſo from <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall juſt mention a few inferences which we may make from what hath been ſaid, and then proceed.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:61584:18"/>
            <p n="1">1. Hence we ſee upon what Foundation that part of the Eſtabliſh'd Doctrine of the Churches of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> is built, which aſſerts that <hi>Epiſcopal Power,</hi> in the Senſe in which we underſtand it, was exerciſed by the Apoſtles, and by their Succeſſors made by them, by vertue of the Commiſſion which they receiv'd from <hi>Chriſt.</hi> This we find in the <hi>Book of Conſecration,</hi> which is Approv'd of by the <hi>Articles</hi> of our <hi>Churches, Art.</hi> 36. Confirm'd by Act of <hi>Parliament,</hi> and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed to by all who have taken <hi>Holy Orders.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. We ſee what reaſon the Reformed Churches abroad had to ſpeak ſo honourably of our <hi>Engliſh Epiſcopacy,</hi> as they have frequently done: for which at large I may refer to Dr. <hi>Durell</hi>'s <hi>View of the Government of thoſe Churches,</hi> and to his later <hi>Defence</hi> of the <hi>Church of</hi> England, in <hi>Latin.</hi> As to their own Practice, To urge their having no <hi>Biſhops,</hi> which their Superiours who are of another perſuaſion will not allow of, as an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument againſt our <hi>Biſhops,</hi> is as unreaſonable as it would be to perſwade us now to Aſſemble for the Publick Worſhip of God, in <hi>Caves</hi> and <hi>Dens;</hi> becauſe the good <hi>Old Chriſtians</hi> being not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by their Perſecutors to have Churches, were forced to do ſo. And we may ſay to them, what a moſt Reverend Prelate of ours did write to one of their Ableſt Divines, <hi>Non culpa veſtra,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:61584:19"/>ſed injuria temporum, abeſſe Epiſcopatum.</hi> 
               <note n="(y)" place="bottom">Biſhop <hi>Andrew</hi>'s Letter to <hi>Du Moulin,</hi> inter Opera Poſth.</note> You have no <hi>Biſhops,</hi> not becauſe you would not, but becauſe ye <note n="(z)" place="bottom">When at the Synod of <hi>Dort,</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Landaff</hi> had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timated That the want of <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> had occaſioned thoſe divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions in the <hi>Netherlands, Bogerman</hi> the Preſident of the Synod ſtood up, and in good allowance of what had been ſpoken ſaid, <hi>Domine, nos. non ſumus adeo felices.</hi> So Biſhop <hi>Hall.</hi>
               </note> cannot have them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Hence we ſee how little foundation there is in <hi>Scripture,</hi> or in <hi>Antiquity,</hi> for any other Forms of <hi>Church-Government.</hi> For to ſay that the <hi>Claſſical,</hi> or that the <hi>Congregational way</hi> (which ſome think <hi>Socinus</hi> invented) was uſed by the Apoſtles, and by their immediate Succeſſors, and yet not the leaſt appearance of them in the <hi>Acts</hi> or <hi>Epiſtles,</hi> and that they ſhould never be heard of for <hi>Fifteen Hundred Years</hi> together, is an Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion ſo very ſtrange, that one might with as much modeſty and reaſon go about to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade us, that the <hi>Caeſars</hi> (whom we have hitherto taken for other kind of <hi>Officers</hi>) were but <hi>Maſters</hi> of the <hi>Corporations</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> or <hi>Chairmen of their Committees.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly and Laſtly,</hi> From hence we may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, how highly inſolent and preſumptuous it would be in us to prefer any new fangled Scheme
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:61584:19"/>of <hi>Government,</hi> before that which was founded by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and exerciſed by his <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and by the whole <hi>Church,</hi> to our days. And certainly Generations to come will look upon this laſt as a very wild Age, in which ſo many People <note n="(a)" place="bottom">The Solemn League and Covenant. <hi>Art.</hi> 2. That without Reſpect of Perſons, They would endeavour to Extirpate Papacy, Prelacy, that is, the Government Eccleſiaſtical by Arch-Biſhops, Biſhops, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> bound themſelves by an <hi>Oath</hi> to Extirpate ſuch a Government.</p>
            <p>But yet, allowing a great part of what hath been diſcourſed, Two things are ſuppoſed by ſome to make a great difference between ours and the Primitive Epiſcopacy. <hi>Their Temporal Juriſdictions, and their Titles and Eſtates.</hi> To which I ſhall only ſay that our <hi>Biſhops</hi> do Claim no <hi>Temporal Juriſdiction</hi> by an inherent Right, as <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and Exerciſe it only by the Favour and Authority of the <hi>King.</hi> And to ſuppoſe that a Princes giving great Titles, and Honours, and Eſtates to <hi>Biſhops,</hi> do's render them not <hi>Chriſtian and Apoſtolical Biſhops,</hi> is very like ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing, that the fairly Binding up and Guilding, and Enamelling a <hi>Bible,</hi> do's make it ceaſe it to be <hi>the Word of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:61584:20"/>
            <p>Having diſcourſed thus largely in order to a Reſolution of the <hi>Firſt Enquiry,</hi> Time will not allow that I ſpeak ſo fully to thoſe that are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind; and therefore I ſhall contract what I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive neceſſary, into as little compaſs as I can.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Second Enquiry</hi> was, concerning the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages of this ſort of Government above others.</p>
            <p>And here two very conſiderable Advantages are obvious to us both from Reaſon and Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> In reference to the Peace of the Church. St. <hi>Hierom,</hi> of all the Fathers leaſt favourable to Epiſcopacy, having (as he thought) been unkindly dealt with by the Biſhop of <hi>Hieruſalem;</hi> does plainly profeſs That the Peace of Particular Churches cannot be preſerved without this Government. His words are, <note n="(b)" place="bottom">In his Dialogue <hi>adverſus Luciferianos.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Eccleſiae ſalus in ſummi Sacer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotis dignitate pendet, cui ſi non exors quaedam &amp; ab omnibus eminens detur poteſtas, tot in Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiis efficientur ſchiſmata, quot Sacerdotes.</hi> Take away the Dignity of the <hi>Biſhop</hi> and you ruin the Church, and if you will not allow him a Power above all, and in which they have no ſhare, you ſhall have as many Schiſms made as
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:61584:20"/>there be <hi>Presbyters.</hi> 'Tis St. <hi>Cyprian</hi>'s Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation <note n="(c)" place="bottom">Neque enim aliunde Haereſes abortae ſunt, aut nata ſunt Schiſmata, quam inde quod Sacerdoti Dei non obtemperatur, nec unus in Eccleſiâ ad tempus Sacerdos, &amp; ad tempus Judex vice Chriſti cogitatur. 'Tis the 59th. Epiſt. in the New Edition. <hi>Pag.</hi> 121.</note> in his 55th. Epiſtle, That <hi>moſt of the Schiſms which have haraſs'd and diſgrac'd the Church, have proceeded from diſobedience to the Biſhop.</hi> And <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 69. <note n="(d)" place="bottom">Inde Schiſmata &amp; haereſes obortae ſunt &amp; oriuntur, dum Epiſcopus qui unus eſt &amp; Eccleſiae praeeſt, Superbâ. quorundam praeſumptione contemnitur, &amp; homo dignatione Dei honoratus indignus ab Hominibus judicatur.</note> He ſays, That the Contempt of the Biſhop will naturally end in Schiſm and Hereſy. And <hi>Calvin,</hi> 
               <note n="(e)" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Calvin</hi> Inſt. <hi>Cap.</hi> 8. <hi>Sect.</hi> 53.</note> as he ſuppoſes Epiſcopacy to be of human inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſo he ſays it was Eſtabliſhed, <hi>Ne ex aequalitate, ut fieri ſolet diſſidia naſcerentur.</hi> To prevent thoſe Contentions which are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly occaſion'd by Equality. And our late Experience tells us how the Church was di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided and ſubdivided, among us in the Late Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Times, when the Biſhops were by the prevailing Party, by force driven from their Charges; the evil effects of which we are yet too ſenſible of. In ſhort, a Biſhop cannot have any deſign in diſturbing the Peace of the Church, and in occaſioning Separations; he can have no
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:61584:21"/>Advantage by it, and conſequently no Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to it, which I need not ſay, Others may have.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> In reference to the Civil Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, happineſs of the State, and eaſe of the Subject. When other Forms of Church Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment were in the Aſcendant in <hi>England,</hi> it cannot yet be forgotten what Diminution and Prejudice to the Royal Honour and Proſperity attended them. I need not put your in mind, how Seditious, Inſolent, Turbulent and Ungo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernable, <note n="(f)" place="bottom">See the Character the King gives of them in his <hi>Baſili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con Doron.</hi>
               </note> King <hi>James</hi> to his great Grief, found the <hi>Presbyteries</hi> in <hi>Scotland</hi> for many Years together; and what uſage his Son, ſince Martyr'd, did many Years after receive from them. It may be demonſtrated that They who ſpeak ſeverely againſt the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> for being (as they pretend) Enemies to the Civil Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, in claiming their Authority from God, do the ſame themſelves, only with far leſs rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and with much greater injury to their Prince. Thus the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Model and Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, though never heard of the World till within theſe laſt <hi>Two Hundred Years,</hi> is declared
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:61584:21"/>by them to be the very <hi>Scepter of Chriſt's King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> to which all muſt ſubmit, even Princes, their Thrones and Scepters. The <hi>Independents</hi> pretend the Holy Scripture for theirs, that any Society of men Combining together by common conſent, in a Church-way and Memberſhip, is by <hi>Divine Right,</hi> Free and Abſolute within it ſelf, to Govern its ſelf by ſuch Rules, as it ſhall judge agreeable to Gods Word; without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance or ſubjection in Spiritual Concerns, to any Human Perſon, or Society whatſoever. 'Tis notorious, that the <hi>Presbyters</hi> do Claim to their <hi>Conſiſtories,</hi> Full and Abſolute Spiritual Power and Juriſdiction over Princes themſelves, with Power to Excommunicate them when they ſee Cauſe. And the <hi>Independents</hi> do exempt their Congregations from all Spiritual Subjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Civil Powers. But our Biſhops do neither pretend to Juriſdiction over our King, nor do withdraw their due Subjection from him whom God has made <hi>Supream</hi> upon Earth, over all Perſons, in all Cauſes, Spiritual as well as Temporal within his Dominions.</p>
            <p>And as to the good of the Subject. 'Tis not ſo long ſince <hi>Presbytery</hi> was Eſtabliſhed, and found Intolerable in <hi>England,</hi> and we are not Ignorant how all Parties did contribute to throw it down, 'twas ſo very uneaſie. As for <hi>Independency,</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:61584:22"/>few now know what it is, <note n="(g)" place="bottom">Dr. <hi>A. Stuart</hi> a <hi>Presbyterian,</hi> ſayd, He verily believed that <hi>Independency</hi> cannot but prove the root of all Schiſms and He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies; and by conſequence much worſe than <hi>Popery. Duply</hi> to <hi>M. S. Pag.</hi> 53. See the Papers for Accommodation.</note> and fewer do deſire it. And as for other <hi>Sects,</hi> they are not yet agreed what Government they would have, nor is it likely that ever they will be. Some in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed do fancy <hi>Independency</hi> to be a pretty, eaſy, ſweet, gentle thing. But certainly, for men to cry out againſt the Yoke of <hi>Biſhops</hi> as intole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, and yet to make every <hi>Pariſh-Miniſter</hi> a <hi>Biſhop;</hi> an Abſolute, Sovereign Independent <hi>Biſhop,</hi> owning no Superiour under Heaven to whom Appeal may be made, is as Ridiculous, as 'twould be to Cry out againſt Monarchy as unſupportable, and to deſire in lieu of it, that every Conſtable be made a King.</p>
            <p>To conclude this point. Many and great Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages hath the Church of God in all Ages enjoyed, and we do now enjoy by this Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and of many of them, like one of the greateſt Bleſſings of this Life, the Health of our Bodies, whilſt we are conſtantly well, we are almoſt inſenſible. But ſtill they are not the leſs for it, though we underſtand them more by their abſence, and can then put the trueſt value
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:61584:22"/>on them, when we ſee others in Feavers and Frenzies, and it may be for their Comfort, in the hands of Empericks too. And ſo I come to the</p>
            <p>Third Enquiry, <hi>What may be reaſonably ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected from Perſons intruſted with that Sacred Power and Authority,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was not only St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Charge to <hi>Titus,</hi> after he had made him a <hi>Biſhop, To ſhew himſelf in all things a Pattern of good works,</hi> but he alſo makes it a neceſſary qualification to every Biſhop, that he be <hi>Blameleſs.</hi> And with great reaſon. For we know that for one in that Dignity to be wicked, is the boldeſt Affront and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour to God himſelf, and one of the moſt fatal miſchiefs to his <hi>Church</hi> imaginable, ſo dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, that a vicious <hi>Biſhop</hi> would not be looked on ſo much as a Governour, as a publick Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; over our heads. Beſides Vice hath this property, that it renders all men contemptible, moſt of all Clergy-men, becauſe 'tis their bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs and profeſſion to make men good, and among them, They who are of the higheſt Rank ſhall be the more ſignally deſpiſed, and thereby made clearly unſerviceable. It will therefore be juſtly expected that they do not contradict their Divine and Holy Doctrines, and make uſeleſs their Authority, by their looſe and unſanctified Lives.</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:61584:23"/>
            <p>Farther, 'Twas St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Charge, That they <hi>ſhould ſpeak the things that become ſound Doctrine, exhort and convince Gainſayers, and rebuke with all Authority.</hi> And indeed men will ſuppoſe that Power was committed to them to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent that they ſhould make ſome uſe of it; and that we are made ſubject to them, that they may compel us if there be occaſion, to do our duties. And now that there is ſo miſerable a decay of all Devotion and Piety, that men are ſo looſe in ther Principles, and ſo corrupt in their Lives, that the <hi>Church</hi> is ſo deſpiſed, and <hi>Religion</hi> it ſelf ſo commonly ſuppos'd a Cheat, or made one: it may be humbly ſuppoſed; that theſe Reverend Perſons, will labour to reduce Offenders by the Cenſures of the Church, and make ſome uſe of Eccleſiaſtical Diſcipline, ſo long, by the misfortunes of the times, diſuſed, that we are juſt upon the point of forgetting that ever there was ſuch a thing; and that they will do this with Vigour and Reſolution, though they know 'twill prove, as of neceſſity it muſt, very ungrateful to many; and though they thereby procure ever ſo much ill will, and gain for, it among us only Curſes from the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane, and graver Reproaches from the Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>critical. This is a Time to ſhew <hi>their Zeal for the Houſe of God,</hi> a Time to ſhew their Chriſtian
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:61584:23"/>Fortitude and Conſtancy; and ſeeing they are ſo well furniſh'd with Power by their Lord and Maſter, and ſo much Countenanced by an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Prince, we may expect that they will not, like thoſe <hi>Children of Ephraim,</hi> 
               <note n="(h)" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> lxxviii.</note> of whom King <hi>David</hi> tells us, <hi>being harnaſſed and carrying Bows, turn themſelves back in the day of Battle.</hi> And 'twill be thought but reaſonable, that as they ingage themſelves in it, ſo they will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect thoſe perſons who are Active and Zealous in the Churches Service, from the unworthy and vile entertainments of thoſe who hate the <hi>Church.</hi> All this men will make bold, and think they may be juſtly allowed, to expect from them. In fine, They ſtand in view of many critical and malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Obſervers, and therefore muſt <hi>Walk Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectly,</hi> becauſe the <hi>days are</hi> ſo very <hi>Evil.</hi> Above all conſidering, that from them, as St. <hi>Paul,</hi> 
               <note n="(i)" place="bottom">Hebr. <hi>xiii. 17.</hi> Canon. Apoſt. <hi>40.</hi> C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                     <desc>••…</desc>
                  </gap>. Concil. Antioch.</note> the <hi>Canons</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and of the <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Antioch,</hi> teach us, God will exact an Account of all the Souls committed unto them. And may they imitate the Holineſs and Integrity, the Juſtice, Charity, Temperance, Humility and Zeal of their worthy Predeceſſors, in the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:61584:24"/>Times; that ſo having been thus <hi>Wiſe,</hi> 
               <note n="(k)" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> xii. 3.</note> and ſuch <hi>Teachers,</hi> they may hereafter <hi>ſhine as the brightneſs of the Firmament,</hi> and having <hi>turned many unto Righteouſneſs, as the Stars for ever and ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo I come in the Fourth and Laſt place, briefly to conſider, <hi>What Honour and Reſpect is due to them from us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As theſe Reverend Perſons are of God's own Appointment, ſo their Labours are for our great and unſpeakable Advantage, and therefore we cannot but believe that they ought to be Loved and Honour'd by us. Nature dictates to us, that God is to be Worſhipped, and therefore they who are immediately inſtrumental and aſſiſtant to us in holy Services, are to have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable reſpect, it being one of the principal ways we have of ſhewing how much we honour God. Some call the univerſal Practice of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, the Voice of Nature; and therefore would time allow, I might here take occaſion to tell you out of Antient Hiſtorians; <note n="(l)" place="bottom">Strabo. Geog. Lib. <hi>2.</hi> Pag. <hi>346. &amp;</hi> Pag. <hi>384. &amp;</hi> Lib. <hi>17.</hi> Pag. <hi>566.</hi>
               </note> That among the <hi>Albans</hi> the Prieſts had the Honour next to the King; Of the great Dignity of the Prieſts among
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:61584:24"/>the <hi>Comani,</hi> and in <hi>Meroe,</hi> and of the Reſpect pay'd to the <hi>Druids.</hi> That the King of <hi>Sparta</hi> was Prieſt of <hi>Jupiter.</hi> That <hi>Plutarch</hi> tells us, that among the <hi>Grecians,</hi> the Prieſthood was of equal Dignity with the Kingdom. <note n="(m)" place="bottom">Quaeſt. Rom. <hi>110.</hi>
               </note> That <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle</hi> teſtifies the ſame in many places of his <hi>Politicks.</hi> That the Roman <hi>Pontifex Maximus,</hi> had his <hi>Sella Curulis</hi> and <hi>Lictors,</hi> as the <hi>Conſuls</hi> had, and that the <hi>Emperous</hi> were often <hi>Ambitious</hi> of that Office.</p>
            <p>To proceed. That <hi>Melchiſedec</hi> was a King and a Prieſt, that the Princes of <hi>On</hi> and <hi>Midian,</hi> were Prieſts, that great was the Dignity of the High-Prieſt, and of the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or Ruler of the Synagogue among the <hi>Jews.</hi> That in the New Teſtament our Biſhops are often peculiarly En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled Gods Servants, and therefore we muſt Acknowledge that 'twill not be for his Honour that they who are his Domeſticks and immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate Attendants, be trampled on, be in want, in meanneſs and diſgrace. <note n="(n)" place="bottom">St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaking of his own being Slandered, uſeth the Word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which in Scripture peculiarly ſignifies, <hi>Speaking <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nworthily of God,</hi> which we call Blaſphemy: as Obſerv'd by the Reverend Biſhop <hi>Sanderſon,</hi> on <hi>Rom.</hi> iii. 8.</note> They are repreſented to be God's Heralds, Embaſſadors, and as it
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:61584:25"/>were his Reſidents among men, and ſuch have ever been held honourable, and their Perſons inviolable, among even the moſt Barbarous People. That the good Old Chriſtians <note n="(o)" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Vid.</hi> Pet. de Marc. Tom. <hi>2.</hi> Pag. <hi>53. &amp;</hi> Pag. <hi>397.</hi>
               </note> paid their Biſhops the greateſt Veneration, even the Emperour <note n="(p)" place="bottom">Lib. <hi>3.</hi> de Vita Conſtantini. &amp; Theod. Hiſt. Eccl.</note> 
               <hi>Conſtantine</hi> himſelf, ſo great honour, that this Age will not bear the very mentioning of it. That in the Fourth and Fifth Centuries, the Learned Fathers both of the <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Latin</hi> Churches, gave to the Biſhops the Titles of <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipes.</hi> So St. <hi>Hilary</hi> in the beginning of his Eighth Book <hi>De Trinitate,</hi> calls them <hi>Principes Eccleſiae.</hi> And <hi>Gregory Nazianzen,</hi> who was ſo Humble and Pious, that rather than that the Peace of the Church ſhould be diſturbed, he did in the firſt <hi>Conſtantinopolitan</hi> Council, reſign the great <hi>Patriarchate</hi> of that City and retire, do's challenge theſe Titles. That the good People <note n="(q)" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Greg. Nazianzen. Orat.</hi> 17. To the Biſhop are aſcribed <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> gave the greatſt Expreſſions of concern for St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> when Baniſh'd, for <hi>Nazianzen</hi>'s Father when Sick, <note n="(r)" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Chryſoſt. Tom.</hi> 4. <hi>p.</hi> 763. Edit. Paris.</note> and for <hi>Baſil</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Caeſarea,</hi> 
               <note n="(s)" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Nazian. Orat.</hi> 19. <hi>pag.</hi> 304. Edit. Paris. 1609.</note> when he lay a Dying. Inſtances of this ſort
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:61584:25"/>are infinite. I might ſhew at large, how great Reſpect the Foreign <hi>Reformed Divines</hi> of moſt Note, have payed to our Biſhops, particularly that <hi>Calvin, Beza, Sadeel,</hi> nay the whole <hi>Conſiſtory</hi> of Paſtors at <hi>Geneva,</hi> that <hi>Danaeus, Peter Martyr, Gualierus, Spanhemius</hi> and others, do in their Works call our Biſhops, <hi>Lords,</hi> and <hi>Moſt Reverend Fathers in God;</hi> enough one would think to ſecure the Title from being <hi>Antichriſtian;</hi> and I might mention what ours, and all the Wiſeſt Princes of <hi>Europe</hi> have thought due to them. In ſhort, we are not to learn our duties from the corrupt practice of a Profane, Atheiſtical Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, nor of ſome men of late years, famous only for being Ill-natur'd, and Troubleſome.</p>
            <p>We know the evil Conſequences of making the Clergy and way Contemptible, and may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve King <hi>Solomon,</hi> 
               <note n="(t)" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> ix. 16.</note> at leaſt our own Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, that the <hi>Poor,</hi> the deſpis'd <hi>Man's Wiſdom is deſpiſed, and his words are not heard.</hi> We find that <hi>Moſes</hi> knowing that he was ſoon to be <hi>gathered to his People,</hi> beſought God that he would pleaſe to Appoint one to ſucceed him, and thereupon God commanded him to take <hi>Joſhua,</hi> and <hi>lay his hand upon him, and to give him a
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:61584:26"/>Charge before all the Congregation,</hi> and adds <note n="(u)" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Numbers,</hi> xxvii. 20. Inſignia poteſtatis geſter, frequenti famulitio cingatur. So <hi>Toſtat. Tirin. Bonfrer. Serrar,</hi> &amp;</note> 
               <hi>And thou ſhalt put ſome of thine Honour upon him, that all the Congregation of the Children of</hi> Iſrael <hi>may he Obedient.</hi> Some of thine Honour. This many Learned <hi>Commentators</hi> ſuppoſe to be Enſigns of Authority, Attendants extraordinary, and other Circumſtances that uſually procure Reſpect; which we ſee God himſelf thought neceſſary, in order to gain their Obedience. So that it cannot be Religion which labours to make thoſe Perſons Low and Sordid, and Mean and Contemptible, and Uſeleſs, whoſe Contempt and Meanneſs renders Religion it ſelf ſo.</p>
            <p>Beſides, were not Religion, were not the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick good ſo much concerned in their Uſage, to deal ingenuouſly, and to ſpeak it out plainly, it cannot but be thought a hard Caſe, that Men who came into the World with perhaps as good Parts, and as fit for Honour and for great Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as their Neighbours, after they have had an Education Liberal and Ingenuous, and all the Improvements of Wit and Judgment, Reaſon and Eloquence; after many Years exhauſting
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:61584:26"/>their Spirits, and waſting their Vigour in publick Services (as our Bleſſed Saviour, <hi>after going about and doing good,</hi> was <hi>arrayed in Purple</hi> that he might be <hi>ſet nought by</hi> Herod <hi>and his Men of War)</hi> ſhould be condemned to a Sacred Station of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Dignity and Authority, only that they may be the more expoſed to Envy and Malice, Hatred and Contempt, be the more eminently deſpiſed, and more auguſtly ridiculous.</p>
            <p>And has this Order deſerv'd ſuch uſages at our hands? How many of it have we had even in this laſt Century in theſe Kingdoms, who have been of Primitive Piety and True Learning, an Honour to their Country, and Examples for future Ages, Able and Couragious Defenders of the Truth, Zealous Oppoſers of <hi>Romiſh Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition,</hi> (that I ſay not the very Bulwarks of <hi>Proteſtancie</hi>) moſt admirable Writers, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable Preachers? And, (by which one may judge of the unreaſonableneſs of our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Clamours againſt them) I may add, That no <hi>Anti-Epiſcopal</hi> man, of what denomination ſoever hath in the judgment of unprejudiced Perſons, written ſo Learnedly and Solidly, againſt the <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> though Aſpers'd themſelves with <hi>Popiſh</hi> Inclinations and Deſigns, as the Late Murdered Primate of <hi>England,</hi> in his Book againſt <hi>Fiſher,</hi> the Late Primate of <hi>Ireland</hi> in
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:61584:27"/>ſeveral of his Treatiſes, and the Late Biſhop of <hi>Durham,</hi> concerning the <hi>Canon</hi> of the <hi>Scripture,</hi> and <hi>Tranſubſtantiation;</hi> to name no others.</p>
            <p>But we have a ſort of men among us, from whoſe Scorn and Reproaches, no Innocence, no Vertue, no Learning, no Prudence or Caution, can Protect either the Fathers, or the Sons of the Church. Be they what they will, they are <hi>all become abominable and gone out of the way, there is none that does good, no not one.</hi> As if a man muſt of neceſſity, be forſaken of God, and of all Goodneſs, as ſoon as he is ingaged in his more immediate Service; and loſe his Wits, at leaſt, part with all ſenſe of Piety and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, as ſoon as he enters upon any Spiritual Office, ſo it be by Law Eſtabliſhed. I wiſh there were no reaſon for this Complaint. But the Injury extends farther than to the preſent Clergy.</p>
            <p>A Leading-Man among the <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> has lately added to his great number of Books, with which he had favoured the World, One which he calls a <hi>Church-Hiſtory,</hi> or <hi>Hiſtory</hi> of <hi>Biſhops;</hi> which the Learned <hi>Anſwerer</hi> juſtly Stiles, <hi>An Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of all the faults which Biſhops have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in the ſeveral Ages of the Church;</hi> and I may add, a great many of their Vertues made Faults. And what can be the deſign of ſuch a
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:61584:27"/>Work as this, but to ſupply what is wanting in the Prelates now Living, to make the Order odious, by relating all the defects of thoſe in former Ages? But alaſs! this is a Melancholy Conſideration, and muſt needs make a ſad im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion on any Pious Soul. For though we cannot think it ſtrange, that Men who are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed Enemies of God, and of all Religion, and would feign laugh them both out of the World, do endeavour to expoſe, and to make ridiculous and odious thoſe perſons whoſe work and ſtudy it is to keep up a ſenſe of Religion upon mens hearts; yet that men, who pretend to be Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly diſpoſed, and heartily concerned for the Honour of God and of the Goſpel, ſhould take much pains to diſgrace, and to render ſuch vile and abominable; this, this is a lamentable indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of a degenerate Age, of an Age ready to be over-run with Profaneneſs and Impiety, and induſtrious to force God to take away the Light of the Goſpel from among them.</p>
            <p>It muſt be Acknowledged that the beſt of men are ſtill but men, and therefore liable to ſome miſtakes and defects. So that it does not appear fair and equitable, that they who, it may take no Notice of Great and Extravagant Faults among their own Party, ſhould moſt ſeverely Cenſure and Aggravate the leaſt Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriage
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:61584:28"/>in a Prelate; as if they diſliked the Cauſe and the Perſons, and not the Crimes, or thought that they ſtricter Piety of the Biſhops, like the Offering of the High Prieſt among the <hi>Jews;</hi> were to <hi>make Attonement for the Sins of the People.</hi> I come not here to flatter any man, or to make Apologies for their Vices, and think I have not as far as became me, ſpoken too favourably of Vicious Prelates, if any happen to be ſo. But 'tis abſolutely neceſſary, (though it will not pleaſe all) that the People be told their duty plainly in this point, and I know not a more proper occaſion, and therefore omitting to ſpeak of the Zeal and Diligence of ſome, and of the Haſtineſs, Credulity and Uncharitableneſs of others, I ſhall in a word or two ſhew how eaſie a thing it is to ſlur a falſe colour on then moſt innocent Actions of the beſt men, and conſequently how little Notice Sober Perſons ſhould take of the Invectives we daily hear againſt our Spiritual Governours. How eaſie a thing is it if they will not by ſervile com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliances Fawn upon, and vilely Court thoſe whom they ſhould Command, to call them Proud? If they will not let their Honour lie in the duſt, and allow that their Office is as Contemptible as their Enemies would have it be, to repreſent them as Ambitious? and how
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:61584:28"/>natural is it for thoſe who pretend that making them poor would make them humble, to make them look as if they were proud, that it may be thought neceſſary to humble them? Be they ever ſo Charitable to the Poor, ever ſo Juſt and Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous in their dealings, if they will not part with the Churches Right to any litigious Perſon, can they forbear calling them Covetous? And, which is a very faſhionable Calumnie now, and almoſt in the mouth of every one of one ſort, if they do but perſwade the People <hi>to Obey Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates</hi> as Chriſtianity obliges them, and will not joyn with the diſcontented in their unreaſonable jealouſies of their Prince, how eaſie is it to ſay, that They are for Tyranny and Arbitrary Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? As if they had not as true a Property in their Eſtates, and as good a Title in Law as any Freeholder in the Kingdom; which all muſt Acknowledge, unleſs they will have Property, ſo highly magnified, to be a word that ſignifies nothing, but in the concerns of a Lay-man; and they who ſtand up for it ſo warmly, mean only their own. If they be for a grave and regular devotion, is it difficult to ſay. They are Popiſh? and if they would have men reverent in Divine Offices, to revile them as Superſtitious? and if any one venture to ſay theſe dealings are not fair and honeſt, to vote him Ambitious, and a
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:61584:29"/>Flatterer? But if theſe be the Crimes of our Biſhops, may they ever be guilty of them; and if they be, under the moſt invidious Character, and with ever ſo much diſ-ingenuity, repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to the World upon theſe Accounts, and be ever ſo much hated and contemned for them, They have this Comfort, that <hi>God,</hi> from whom they expect their Reward, <hi>ſeeth not as man ſees,</hi> and that whilſt we <hi>regard</hi> only the <hi>outward ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance,</hi> he views <hi>the heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>To make an End of all.</q>
            <p>May I not be allowed to beſeech you with ſome earneſtneſs, that if you have any Love for the Truth, any Zeal for the Goſpel, and any Concern for the Peace and Proſperity of the Church: That you will not ſuffer your ſelves to be prejudiced by the heat and importunities of none of the moſt knowing and peaceable men, againſt a Government built upon a foundation of <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s own Inſtitution, Exerciſed by the Holy Apoſtles, and continued from them to us? the only Government uſed in all Ages by the whole Chriſtian Worlds; honoured and reverenced by all, and adminiſtred by many of the Holy Fathers, Martyrs and Confeſſors; acknowledged by all <hi>Councils,</hi> honoured by all the worthy <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:61584:29"/>Learnedeſt nf the Forreign Reformers, and highly Reſpected and Advanced by all Chriſtian Kings and Princes; and never oppoſed in the Antient Church by any, but by one deſperate man, immediately branded for a Heretick upon that Attempt? And let us not be drawn unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countably into a Kindneſs for any Novel, Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain and Arbitrary Form, one thing to day, and we know not what to morrow, to the diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance of our quiet, and for ought as we can tell, to the Ruin and Deſolation of theſe three Flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Kingdoms; to the Eternal Shame and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace of the <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> nay of the <hi>Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> and the great Joy and Triumph of the Enemies of all Religion, and of God himſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſider what hath been ſaid, and the Lord give You underſtanding in all things.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
